Welcome back to another C++ networking
video. We are back at it again with
HTTP. So, last time we used this pretty
cool library called HTTP lib. Here it is
on GitHub. I'll leave a link to it in
the description below. So, we
specifically focused on the client side
functionality of this library. How can
we use this library to request things
via HTTP from the internet and we set up
a server using Hostinger and we
basically had two different examples
that showed how to actually use this.
Definitely check out that video if
you're interested. This is kind of the
continuation because today we're going
to be focusing on the server side of all
of this. Rather than me writing some
kind of application in C++ to run like
on my Windows computer for example and
requesting some kind of data via HTTP
like we did last time, we're going to be
serving that data now. So we're going to
be on the server server side doing some
HTTP
serving. Look at me. I am the server
now. So, if we have a little look at
what we did last time, we have this HTTP
client in use here. In this example,
we're actually just getting the weather
asynchronously. There it is. 11.4°
Celsius in November. Late November in
Melbourne, Australia is very rough. I
have no idea why it's so cold. Anyway,
we also had this other example over
here, simple example, which was
accessing our server. So, this IP
address is our server that we set up
using Hostinger. And then you can see
we're just using HTTP get on this page
specifically. And the result is whatever
we put into that file. So this
specifically from our server was being
served using engine X. Engine X is a web
server. It's an HTTP server amongst
other things. It's basically an
application that functions as a server
as an HTTP server. But what if we want
to write our own? We're C++ programmers.
We should be able to do anything, right?
I don't want to use EngineX. I don't
want to use Apache. I want to serve my
own files using code that I write using
a third party library. Of course, I'm
not going to write from scratch. I mean,
I could, but who has time for that in
this economy? So, how convenient that
this HTTP lib, this beautiful library,
has not just a client example, but also
a server example. It must be this easy,
right? So, step one, get a server. Step
two, write some C++ code on it. I guess
we might as well compile the code on the
actual server itself. And then we'll
execute our C++ program on the server.
And then we basically don't need engine
X anymore. we can just serve our own
stuff, but we can really write whatever
code we want to serve any kind of data.
I guess theoretically we'll be able to
do anything. So, let's get started. Step
one, as I mentioned, is we need a
server. And for that, I'm going to use
Hostinger, the sponsor of this video.
Hostinger is by far my favorite web host
on the internet, and I've been through a
few. Hostinger servers are super
affordable, but they don't cut corners.
They're really highquality servers. If
you go to hosting.com/churner, the first
thing you'll notice is they're actually
having a Black Friday sale on at the
moment. This is the biggest sale of the
year. This is the biggest sale of the
year. Now is definitely the time to
actually get yourself a server. You can
see that they use AMD Epic processes and
NVME SSD storage on all of their
servers, making them perform really
well. If you have a look at their VPS
plans, you'll see that they're all KVM
servers. What does KVM mean? Hostinger
has an entire page on this, but
basically all you need to know is that
it allows a VPS to function as a
completely independent server. One of my
favorite things as well is that you can
easily scale your plan. So you can just
start off with the small one and then if
you find that you need more, you can
seamlessly upgrade. All of these KVM
servers come with full route access
which we're going to need to be able to
create our C++ application and execute
it. All of their plans also come with
free weekly backups and excellent DOS
protection and security. Let's go ahead
and pick this KVM2 plan. And then at
checkout, make sure you click on this
have a coupon code button and you use
coupon code churno to get an even bigger
discount. You'll get an additional 10%
off. Setting up your server is super
easy. All you have to do is pick a
location for it. Hosting have a bunch of
data centers worldwide and you'll be
able to see what your ping is to any
given location which I think is really
cool. You'll need to pick an operating
system. They have a huge range to choose
from. Abuntu 24 is usually what I go
with. And then finally set a root
password and you are done. The setup
takes only a couple minutes and then
you'll be greeted with this beautiful
dashboard. From there you're ready to
SSH into your server and get started. As
I mentioned, Hostinger is currently
having their Black Friday sale. This is
their biggest sale of the year. So, head
on over to hosting.com/churno and use
coupon code churn at checkout and get
yourself an amazing server. Huge thank
you to Hostinger as always for
sponsoring this video. Okay, so once we
have acquired a server, let's go ahead
and write some C++ code to create an
HTTP server and run it on our server.
So, as I've mentioned throughout my
videos, my favorite way to do this kind
of stuff is to install this remote SSH
extension in VS Code. This is it by
Microsoft. I'll leave a link to it in
the description below. Once you have
that installed, what I have over here,
I've opened up my server. You can see
the IP address over here. I've opened
this up in VS Code and I'm in a
directory. It's blank. We're going to do
this like from scratch now because it's
really simple. Like it's really simple.
The first thing I want to do is open up
a new terminal. We're going to try and
make a C++ application here. So, you
need to have some sort of compiler. I
have Clang installed. I can just type in
Clang. Hit enter. You can see it clearly
works. Otherwise, you'll probably have
to do something like this after apt
update. I already have this installed.
So, I'm ready to go. That's probably it.
So, to test everything and make sure
it's working, I'm going to make this
main CPP file. I'm just making it in
this directory. I'm not even making a
source directory for it. This is just
going to be a really simple example, and
we're going to try and keep it as simple
as possible with this remote SSH
extension. By the way, you can also
rightclick and create new files and
folders. So, you don't have to do it via
the command line if you don't want to.
Okay. So, in this file, let's write some
C++ code. So, I'll include IO stream.
We'll do int main. Look at that. We've
already got a hello world program
written for us by AI. I'll get rid of
the return zero even though it really
wants me to add it because you don't
need it. Now let's try and compile this.
So clang++ main.cp and I mean in the
simple case that's probably it. You can
see it's generated this file over here
called a.out. You probably don't want it
to be called that but anyway now we
should just be able to do dot slash and
run that. And you can see we print hello
world programming on a VPS. Absolutely
no issues there at all. Okay. So instead
of outputting this a.out out file. We
can add an output just by doing - o and
then we can call it something like
server. Yay. So now we have uh an actual
application here kind of called server.
Let's go ahead and delete that a.out
file. So now I can basically dot /server
and then I'm running my C++ program.
Awesome. So realistically, you know,
we're keeping things simple. As I
mentioned, that is the name of today's
game I've decided. But if it wasn't,
instead of like recalling this
compilation command every single time
you want to actually build this project,
you could put it into some kind of
script. I would definitely use CMake for
more complicated projects. So you could
generate like make files using CMake and
then run make to actually do the
building. That's just so overkill, but
that's what people tend to do. You
absolutely don't have to for simple
things. And I think this is also why C++
gets such a bad reputation when it comes
to complexity and how hard stuff is to
work with. You can see how easy this is,
right? Like this is super easy. And yes,
it is a hello world program, but we
don't need all of this extra stuff at
all. And extending this to create an
HTTP server is actually also not going
to involve anything more than this. So
let's do that, shall we? So what do we
do now? How do we get this library and
we build it? And I mean, look, there's a
CMake file here, right? So I assume we
should probably like maybe get CMake
installed, convert this into like a
CMake project. Maybe we'll use Git.
We'll clone this library straight onto
the VPS. I think that sounds reasonable.
No, no, stop. This is a single file
header only crossplatform library. So
this is what we actually do because
remember we're in Simple Town tonight
and we're keeping it that way. Where is
the actual file? http lib.h. This is the
file. I'm going to click on raw over
here and then here it is. Here's the
file. I'm going to grab this URL. I'm
going to copy it. And then over here on
my server, I'm just going to type in
curl then that URL. And then because I
don't want it to just I mean, if I run
that, it's just going to like print it
for me over here, which is cool, but I
want it in a file. So, let's take all of
this and we'll copy it and paste it. I'm
just kidding. So, let's run that same
command, but then we're going to use a
right angle bracket here with a file
name. And then it's going to just
basically put all of that log output
into a file for us instead of showing it
to us in the log in the terminal. I mean
it's not really a log. Now that file was
called http lib.h. So I will stay true
to that. http lib.h. So we're putting
the result of all of this into that.
Let's hit enter. There we go. It's
basically instant is done. And here we
have the file. Okay, cool. That was
quick. So now in maincb let's include
http lib.h. We'll save that file. Let's
go ahead clear our terminal and then we
will simply recompile it. And we're kind
of done. By the way, one thing I
probably would add to this for my sanity
is the version of C++ we want to use.
So, for example, C++ 20 like that. And
then if we hit enter, we'll get the same
result. I'm not entirely sure what the
default is if you don't actually specify
this, but that's kind of the issue that
it might change. I think C++ 17 might be
the default for obviously more modern
versions of Clang. Actually, it's kind
of easy to check. So, why don't we just
do that? So, if I include format, which
sd format is a C++ 20 feature. So, if we
go ahead and just try and use format,
maybe just with an empty string, doesn't
really matter. And I try and compile
using this command that doesn't
explicitly specify a C++ version. There
we go. It doesn't exist. But if I go
ahead and now specify C++ 20 and hit
enter, then there we go. We're getting a
warning instead of an error. And that's
just because we're discarding the result
of this and it's not supposed to be
discarded. But you can see that compiles
fine. Now, if we instead use a C++ 17
feature to just see whether or not
that's actually in use, I'll just use
file system path and we'll change this
to be file system and I will compile
without specifying a version. Then you
can see that actually still works. But
file system is a C++ 17 feature. So if I
drop to like C++ 14 and try and compile,
then you can see it doesn't work. So
yes, we have deduced that Clang++
whatever version I have installed, which
I guess I probably should have checked.
Okay. Abuntu Clang version 18.1.3
uses C++ 17 as a default if you don't
specify what version of C++ you'd like
to use. You're welcome. All right. What
were we doing again in this video? Oh
yeah, HTTP server. Sorry about that. So
let's get rid of all of this junk. So
check this out. We're including this and
it's compiling obviously. So now if we
go back to GitHub, let's go ahead and
take a look at that example. So here's
the server multi thread example. Again,
they've got like OpenSL stuff being used
here. You do need more libraries for
that. That actually does realistically
complicate things. So I might revisit
that in a future video. But for now,
let's just use the HTTP version. So let
me just copy like all of this. And then
I'm going to paste it into VS Code.
Let's tab this over. We're going to get
rid of the HTTPS version. I'll tab this
over as well. I think everything else
looks pretty okay. Yeah, I mean that's
basically the example that they had. So
let's get rid of Hello World. So it
should actually serve us Hello World.
Let's change that to hello from C++
server. And then I'm just going to
compile this. I guess we don't really
need to use C++ 20 or anything. We can
just leave it like that. Keep things
simple. Use C++ 17. And then I'm just
going to run our server. And you can
see, by the way, that it compiled with
no issues, no warnings, no nothing. And
it's now running. So that's nice. I
mean, we're not even compiling with
optimization or anything, but that
doesn't really matter for this example.
So what have we actually done? What what
is this program that we've created? What
is it doing? So the example they had
uses http get on the high location right
so this like /h high page to serve us
this content as text plane we're
listening for connections on the local
host port 8080. So if this is actually
working correctly and this port is not
like blocked by the firewall or anything
then if I type in the URL or the IP
address of this server port 8080 /hi and
I hit enter
hello from C++ server. Look at that in
Chrome in a web browser. We're actually
using C++ code to serve data via HTTP
that we can request from any web
browser. I mean check it out. It's
working on my phone. Like of course it's
working on my phone. This is isn't like
the most groundbreaking thing in the
world, but it is really cool because it
was just so easy. It was just so easy to
do this in C++ on a server that I think
a lot of you who are like really scared
of this stuff or you're scared of C++ or
Linux or whatever it may be, you're just
over complicating things. And it's it
might not even be your fault. Like
people around you might be over
complicating things and that really is a
problem. Anyway, so this is a C++
program and you can obviously use this
however you like. You can generate like
the data that you're sending here really
however you like. You could write some
basic like C style file IO if you want.
In fact, let's do that for fun because
AI is kind of helping us. Like we can
just kind of rely pretty much on AI.
Like look at this. I'm just tabbing
across. It doesn't even know what it's
reading. Like what is this code that
it's generating? I mean it seems pretty
good. Also we don't have to use C style
file IO. We can use C++ but I don't
know. I just wrote this. Okay. So here
is basically what it did. Let's stop
this program and we'll see if we can fix
this up. This looks pretty reasonable to
me. So, we're just going to serve
whatever was in that file. The file was
called data.ext. Let's create a new file
called data.ext. And then we'll
basically grab I probably shouldn't
serve the exact same thing. Let's get
rid of this anyway cuz we don't want to
be also doing that. And then in our
file, let's just do like hello from a
file now still C++. And then I'll save
that. Okay, let's go ahead and compile
and we'll run. And now if we refresh our
web browser, hello from a file. Now
still C++ child's play. This is honestly
a really nice library. This HTTP lib
like this is this is how it's meant to
be like as far as C++ goes. It doesn't
have to be complicated at all. Okay, so
the last example I want to show you is
through walnut through our actual client
side C++ code. We can obviously do the
same thing. I mean here we were going to
slap API which by the way is still being
served by engine X like I have not taken
that away. But now if we add port 8080
which is our C++ HTTP server and I do /h
high which is that page that we that
location that we created then check this
out. Now we see hello from a file now
still C++. So we're actually using C++
as the client to request data from a
server that is also something that we
made using C++ and that's serving us
this data across the world. I don't
remember exactly what location I picked
for that hosting server, but yeah, there
you go. I hope you guys enjoyed this
video. It really has been fun taking a
look at this HTTP lib library. I really
quite recommend it. Honestly, I
recommend it as much as I can having
done like judge. I mean, I've basically
just run like this code from the read me
for it, but the fact that it just works
so flawlessly, like this is this is what
I'm all about. There's a lot of
follow-up obviously that I could do to
the stuff that we've taken a look at in
these last two videos. So, let me know
what you'd like to see in the comment
section below. A bunch of you in the
last video who have used this library
more than I have were vouching for just
how good it is. So, that's awesome to
see as well. So, yeah, let me know if
you enjoyed this kind of me like messing
around with some C++ code cuz this is
the first time like I've done something
like this and honestly, it was quite
fun. Thank you all for watching. Don't
forget to check out Hosting's amazing
Black Friday sale using my link
description below and I will see you
next time. Goodbye. New